<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>SKM GEEK&#x27;s Blog - miscellaneous</title>
      <link>https://blog.skmgeek.com/</link>
      <description>Hello! Welcome to my place for putting Things. I share my projects, thoughts, and anything else I feel like here.</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://blog.skmgeek.com/tags/miscellaneous/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>Welcome to the Blog</title>
          <pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>SKM GEEK</author>
          <link>https://blog.skmgeek.com/2025-05-15-welcome-to-the-blog/</link>
          <guid>https://blog.skmgeek.com/2025-05-15-welcome-to-the-blog/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://blog.skmgeek.com/2025-05-15-welcome-to-the-blog/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;hello-welcome-to-my-new-place-for-putting-things&quot;&gt;Hello! Welcome to my new place for putting Things.&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog is where I will share my projects, thoughts, and anything else I feel like.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There isn’t going to be a set schedule or anything, I’ll just post whenever I feel like it. My hope is that this blog will get me to finish projects that I otherwise would have left unfinished, and will serve as an archive showing all the things I’ve done. I might write posts about the projects I’ve already started, or I might not. It depends on what feels worth sharing. I’m quite new to the prospect of writing about everything I do, so it will certainly take a bit of learning. Perhaps this blog will encourage me to do new things just so I can write about them. Time will tell!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is both an &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;rss.xml&quot;&gt;rss&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; and an &lt;a href=&quot;&#x2F;atom.xml&quot;&gt;atom&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; feed available for you to subscribe to, and it would certainly mean a lot to me if you did! Knowing that people are interested in the things I do pushes me to continue doing them.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ll leave this post at that. I may talk about some more blog-related things in the near future, but I think that about sums it up for now.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s a picture of my cat Misty to fill the space (she says hello):

&lt;div class=&quot;img-container&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;image-click&quot; href=&quot;&amp;#x2F;files&amp;#x2F;2025-05-15-misty.jpg&quot;&gt;


    


    
        
    
    
    
    
    
        
        
    
    
        
        &lt;img src=&quot;https:&amp;#x2F;&amp;#x2F;blog.skmgeek.com&amp;#x2F;processed_images&amp;#x2F;2025-05-15-misty.7f756b323aaee443.webp&quot; alt=&quot;A picture of my cat, Misty.&quot; title=&quot;A picture of my cat, Misty. (Click to open in new tab)&quot; width=&quot;301&quot; height=&quot;400&quot; &#x2F;&gt;
    


&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;div&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;-skm&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
